let's turn to National Security advisor
HR McMaster speaking
yesterday he shares information in a way
that is wholly appropriate and I should
just make I should just make maybe this
the statement here that that the
president wasn't even aware you know of
where this information came from he
wasn't briefed on the source of method
of the information either so that's
National Security adviser HR McMaster
who had to come out yesterday after
speaking the day before um uh saying
that none of the New York Times report
The Washington Post report was true um
that and yet uh you have um president
Trump himself contradicting this I
wanted to ask you about the release of
this classified information which you
point out the president can do um and
compare it to your own case where you
released unclassified information John
would you give give us just a thumbnail
um history of what happened to you after
you spent what 14 years at the CIA as an
analyst and a case officer sure I blew
the whistle on the cia's torture program
in December of 2007 the FBI investigated
me for a full year and then determined
that I had not committed a crime and
they closed the case against me but when
President Obama was inaugurated the CIA
asked him to secretly reopen the case
against me and I was investigated for
another three years I had no idea I was
under investigation finally I was
charged with five felonies including
three counts of Espionage and those
Espionage charges resulted from the
passage of an unclassified business card
uh to a journalist from The New York
Times and one from ABC News and the fact
that I had told a reporter that a CIA
former CIA colleague of mine who had
never been undercover uh had worked in
the Osama Bin Laden unit which I hadn't
done in the first place the New York
Times came to me with that information
but that was good enough for three
counts of Espionage and mind you those
names were never made public the the
names of the people I was accused of of
outing but still I I faced 45 years in
prison and ended up doing uh 23
months so compare what's happened with
President Trump right now um right this
is this is really a serious
issue the fact that he's president aside
and that he's allowed to declassify
information there's a process that you
go through to declassify that
information you can't just blur it out
to the Russian foreign minister and the
Russian Ambassador what happens is the
information uh goes back to the CIA to
the originating office the CIA will pull
the relevant information out of the
report put it on a a new blank sheet of
paper and then type at the top secret
releasable to Russia that way nobody
gets inou trouble no sources and methods
are revealed everybody's happy and we
can establish something of a liaison
relationship to the Russians that's not
what the president did now General
McMaster said something very important
yesterday he said that the president was
not aware of the source well if that's
true then shame on General McMaster
because that's his job to make sure that
the president is informed now if he
briefed the president on this
information and didn't tell him the
source or didn't convey to the president
the the clandestinity of this Source
then maybe we should be talking today
about General McMaster
resigning uh John kiraku the New York
Times uh has a remarkable paragraph um
they write in private three
Administration officials conceded they
could not publicly articulate uh their
most compelling and honest defense of
the president for divulging classified
intell to the Russians that Mr Trump a
hasty and indifferent reader of his
briefing materials simply did not
possess the interest or the knowledge of
the granular details of intelligence
gathering to leak specific sources and
methods of intelligence a gathering that
would harm American Allies can you
respond to that again a quote from the
New York Times yeah I I've never heard
I've never heard a White House staff say
that the president was St too stupid or
too ill-informed to have broken the law
and that's really what it comes down to
the truth is he leaked highly classified
information that he shouldn't have
leaked it's one thing to say hey I'm the
president nobody can punish me for that
it's another thing entirely to just deny
that he did it we know that he did it
and he really ought to own up to it
where I'm disappointed is in the
reaction of Republicans on Capitol Hill
I understand Party Loyalty this is
Washington after all but my God you have
to think about what's good for the
Country and this is certainly bad for
the
country um can you talk about Trump
reportedly urging then FBI director
Comey um to consider jailing reporters
for publishing classified
information I I say this in all cander I
think the president very simply has
never read a copy of the Constitution I
think that that that's true he's just
never bothered to read the Constitution
and he just has no understanding
appreciation of the first amendment's
protections um for freedom of speech
with that said there was a very
dangerous precedent that was Set uh
during the Obama Administration when
James ryzen refused to testify in the in
the trial of Jeffrey Sterling another
CIA whistleblower and um James ryzen the
New York Times Reporter James ryzen the
New York Times Reporter and Pulitzer
Prize winner uh he refused to testify
the uh the prosecution in the eastern
district of Virginia appealed to the
fourth Circuit Court of Appeals and the
fourth circuit held that ryzen did have
to testify that case then went to the
Supreme Court and the Supreme Court said
the same thing that ryzen had had to
testify he didn't testify in the end and
attorney general holder didn't prosecute
him for uh not testifying but still the
precedent was set and so I think that
that the problem here is is a bigger one
that than Jim ryzen not testifying or
than Donald Trump saying that we should
Jail uh reporters the the bigger issue
is is this incremental whittling away of
our constitutional rights our most
important constitutional rights
including freedom of speech this is
something that we really have to put our
foot down on and we have to fight it at
every step of the
way can you talk about what your
colleagues um at the CIA another
intelligence agency are saying about
what's happening right now are saying
about President Trump and the Trump
Administration I have a friend uh in the
CIA who called me recently from overseas
and he asked if I had been following the
news and I said oh of course I have I've
been following every detail and he said
do the American people realize how bad
this is and I said I think they do I
think Congress is pretending that it's
not bad but I think the American people
realize that this President so early in
his in his term is just simply out of
control he doesn't understand
intelligence he doesn't understand the
purpose or use of intelligence he
doesn't like or trust the CIA and the
CIA for a little while wasn't sure how
to respond to this I think in the end
the CIA is going to slow roll this
President and what I mean is they know
they can wait him out most senior
officers in the CIA have been in the
organization for 20 25 even 30 years
they've waited out other presidents and
I think that they believe they can wait
out this one that he won't be around for
long can you predict what you think will
happen I mean there is noise on Capitol
Hill among Democrats and some talk among
Republicans of the possibility of
impeachment do you think that's possible
John I think it's possible I don't yet
think that it's probable I think what we
need in the absence of a of a special
prosecutor law which lapsed I believe in
1999 or
1997 uh we need a a special councel we
need a prosecutor who is able to really
do an in-depth investigation and just
see where the where the evidence leads
us uh I think that the evidence will
lead us to several different crimes that
have been committed by uh people around
president Trump and who knows perhaps
there are crimes having been committed
by President Trump so I think we ought
to really look at the Republicans on
Capitol Hill and gauge their support for
this President they reluctantly went
along with him when he finally came out
of the Republican primaries there's not
a whole lot of loyalty there and I think
that if even the Republicans on Capitol
Hill smell blood in the water they'll
begin to turn the first time a
republican member of Congress starts
talking about impeachment I think it's a
slippery slope from there John you spent
14 years at the CIA as an analyst and a
case officer you exposed a bush era um
torture and I was wondering if you can
talk about that
uh the information that you talk to a
reporter about though the reporter
didn't talk reveal any uh name of any
agent uh in your from your conversation
with him you ultimately were jailed talk
about the substance of the information
you were trying to get
out I said three things in the initial
interview that I did with ABC News in
December of 2007 I said that the CIA was
torturing its prison
I said that torture was official US
government policy it was not the result
of a rogue CIA officer as President Bush
had intimated and I said that the
torture program had been personally
approved by the president himself but
that's not specifically why I was jailed
remember the the FBI determined that
what I had said was not a crime and so
they began digging and digging and
digging until they finally were able to
put something together and what it was
was a reporter for ABC News um had
written to me asking for help uh in
writing a book on the cia's rendition
program I told him I didn't know
anything about rendition and I didn't
know anyone involved he sent me a list
of a dozen names I didn't know anybody
he sent me a second list of a dozen
names and I told him you obviously know
this issue so much better than I do I
really can't help you and he finally
said well in your first book what about
a guy that you um met in Pakistan on the
tarmac of uh of an airport and I said oh
you're talking about John Doe I don't
know what ever happened to him he's
probably retired and living in Virginia
somewhere that was a felony because I
had confirmed the name of John Doe now
that happens in Washington every single
day if you pick up a copy of the New
York Times or the Washington Post you're
going to see classified information and
indeed former CIA director David
Petraeus gave the names of 10 covert
officers to his adulterous girlfriend
and was not prosecuted uh in my case
there was another CIA officer a
disgruntled former CIA officer Who
provided this reporter with the names of
seven covert officers he was not uh
prosecuted because he didn't blow the
whistle on the torture
program well John kako thank you so much
for joining us um I want to spend more
time with you at another point to really
go into uh your book John Kaku spent 14
years at the CIA as an analyst and case
officer exposing the bush aor torture
program becoming the only official
jailed in connection with it his Memoir
has just been published it's called
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison this
is democracy now we're broadcasting from
San Diego stay with us